all right hello and
welcome it's 9th of March
2025 we're in active inference guest
stream 99.1 with avel so welcome AEL if
you would like to say hello and go into
your presentation we're looking forward
to it so go for
it hello so i a
I work with Andy Clark who is a
cognitive philosopher at the University
of susex in the context of the Escape
project which is a project on
archaeology um cognitive archaeology uh
and which focuses on the relation
between mind and material culture I'm
also a fing member of Kyo scientific par
academic organization let's think of it
as a think T and what I will uh present
today let us consider it as um an
advertisement for the social science sub
project in the ACT Institute because
it's the aggregation of the work I did
to motivate well necessity for I will
say new mathematics for the study of
social change that are inspired by act
inference but you know much on line with
what is done mathematically to formalize
it so we will go from contextuality to S
constraints and I will try to articulate
an active influence onology for
participatory realism and social change
so uh first let us try to motivate what
is it that we are doing here so human
minds and human culture display a very
clear sign of openend evolution what do
I mean by openend Evolution it is
evolution that is open-ended I'm sorry
this is kind of circular but essentially
you can make new things that did not
exist before before that were not a
thing before that were not a part of
some platonic space of things we made it
up it was made up this is what I mean by
open ended
Evolution and this is true in generally
whatever it is that you man do so for
example we have an impression ofan
escape on the left of the screen and you
know it's buildings we made them up we
built those buildings and they answered
a specific perception of what building
is that did not predate
the concept of building the invention of
building by humans and this is very
manifest for example in writing because
you know writing is this sign the
interactivity of writing rely on signs
being a thing that signs are a thing
only if we look at them as science so we
are looking at letters on the screen and
understand them as being embedded with
meaning but the concept of a c does not
pre-exist Humanity there is no uh C
dimension in the irational way function
at Big Bang we made it up it's in
evolution and the problem of uh
explaining presenting addressing
mathematically and physically the
opended evolution of stuff it's a pretty
huge problem uh St
kofman best physics guy in my opinion is
Carrier to that
and let's be frank it not solid it is
not near to solving it uh because it's a
hard problem because there is this idea
that open-ended change brings out new
stuff and in mathematics we have to
represent an nice space that has
specific possibilities in it else who
are not going far and this seems to be
incoherent with the logic of pen
Devolution so hard
problem um I will jump to cognitive
science because again my interest here
in is in human mind and social
Evolution and I will try to explain what
we mean by explaining in cognitive
science so for schematic purposes I will
say there are three kinds of explanation
that we can go for one is nomological
it's with regard to laws so for example
if I I don't know thr thing and see that
it falls this way I can from nature law
that describes what happens and because
it happens a lot happens every time I
try I claim it is a la I claim that
describing the regularity explains this
activity so it's a phenomological
approach to explanation I just describe
the phenomenal and hope this is
explanatory this is how we do think in
physics not in Psychology not in biology
not in cognitive science not in
sociology what is more natural in those
discipline the special Sciences is a
mechanical explanation so we look at
structure and we show how the structure
entail this in this phenomenon for
example we have the out model of you
know Neal activity which postulates a
bunch of
electrochemistry which if verified and
it seems to be verified explains the
action potential activity of neurons and
I would say pretty close to Mechanical
explanation in the space of POS
explanation are functional explanation
which address not how does it work but
why is it and that is centered on you
know functional hypothesis so it's for
example most of what biologist
evolutionary biologist do it's
hypothesis what why must this happen
because it's selected
for and I would say both you can cluster
those approaches between neological
where you tend to try to describe laws
and mechanical and functional hesis
where we have a more lean approach to
modeling and trying to get into what is
going on in a specific system uh for it
to act like
that and in neuros science uh we are
pretty good at mechanisms this is
according to BU and
Pini the HM Mark of what they call
cognitive neuros sense we assume that
the behavior as we can meure it derives
from cognitive mechanisms those
cognitive mechanisms are mented by the
physical structure of the brain and this
physical structure it's integrated in a
context of operation that involves both
physical physiological and eological
factors so we can look at for example
activation patterns activation in brain
activity and map them into equation here
it's from
doob and it tries to map brain activity
onto reinforcement learning which is U
very uh hype family was at least a very
hype family of algorithm describing
learning so we can explain activity from
structure but what we cannot do with a
mechanistic approach is explain why the
structure is there because you can
describe you can explain activity from
structure but if you try to
explain structure from structure you get
you know rtion to infinite you do not
explain much much or at least you do not
have the possibility to explain without
regressing to the
infinite the argument I will make here
is that both cognitive structure
understood as you know pattern in
cognitive activity and its Evolution
flow from a single phenomena which is
the construction of meaning to cognitive
agency so the structure produce a
function a part of activity which itself
will shade the structure at time t+ one
this is the only way I can think of to
you know at least have a baseline
concept of what it is to study op
Evolution system does stuff stuff
changes system pretty simple I don't see
how we could you know go around
that and to be more precise I will argue
that we exist in a context that is
characterized by social
constraints and that Define what
we agree let us say we can and cannot do
in a given CC text and these constraints
are integrated and elected by
humans and the way they are integrated
and connected kind of ontologically by
construction leads to their
reconstruction and this is what anies
both the structure of cognition through
the integration of thinking in those
system of constraints and the openend
evolution
thereof so
we do active inference this is the
active INF Institute we may as well
explain active
inference
so I guess most people who are attending
to the talk no know what I'm talking
about but this is going on YouTube I
will reference it I need to explain what
active inference is active inference is
uh built from what K Fone and colleagues
proposed as a principle for cognition
that is bed b inference
inference is basically reduces to the
formula you see on screen the
probability of an hypothesis given
evidence is equal to the probability of
an Evidence given hypothesis time
probity of the hesis over probility of
evidence so for example if you hear
barking it's pretty likely there is a
dog unless uh it's very likely there is
a dog near you uh uh for example you are
in an office and the office is closed so
there no dog can enter or unless you
have other explanation for hearing
barkings for example you have a YouTube
tab open with eight hours of barking
noises I don't know why you would but if
you did you would hear barking and
nothing of so this reduces to this
formula uh P of e knowing h means the
probability of hearing barking if there
is a dog probability of h means
probability of having a dog with you
probability of e means probability of
hearing the
barking and you can compute the
probability of having a dog with you
knowing that you heard barking from that
this is most basic stuff you can do in
statistics and uh the thing is there is
no reason why your brain or any single
natural system for that matter could
represent could compute this because you
know uh neurons do action potential they
don't do
numbers so the novelity in fr's approach
is to propose algorithm well more of a
you know physical
process uh that could
approach optimal bii inference so the
optimal inference of hypothesis given
evidence through mization of something
called veral free
energy uh you don't need to know exactly
what this formula is what is important
is that it's something that uh is always
higher to S price so if you minimize our
energy you minimize Sur price you
approach uh perfect ban model of what is
going on around
you
and if you assume that uh NE activity
layer upon layer upon layer of NE
activity self organize
like that to infer the causes of sensory
stimuli uh they will effectively predict
upcoming signal in a way that Nables
adaptive understanding navigation of the
world and this is pretty much what the
active inference uh Paradigm is assuming
that the brain does
that um we will not try to illustrate
what exactly we mean by you know active
infective processing the core idea is
that you brain predicts sensation given
prayer knowledge out of the world so
please look at the screen look at the
sentence in the middle of it do not look
away and pick something in your
peripheral vision for example I'm
picking a water bottle at my right and
while still looking at the screen you
don't glance at the object you picked
you try to make out as much detail as
possible about it I'm going to predict
two things for most of you you will be
confident about knowing what it is you
will see what it is but also you won't
be able to see any single detail that
tells you what it is for example I'm
seeing water bottle I know it is water
bottle but I just see a blue thing I do
not have the detail to know it's water
bottle it could be a vase for all I can
see but I have the information that it
is indeed a water bottle because I put
it there I'm remembering that if I want
to drink I need to fetch it so I know
it's water bottle and I see water
bottle um you can now look away from the
screen so uh what this illustrates is
that your perception is at a pretty
basic level embedded in par knowledge
and this is something that we have known
more or less intuitively since a pretty
long time for example this is the rabbit
and dock illustration that with gin
really liked
and I will predict once again that when
you see this illustration you see either
a rabbit or a duck and you may you know
if I look at the what would be the back
of the head of the rabbit or the mouth
of the uh sorry the back of the head of
the duck or the mouth of the rabbit I
see the rabbit if I look at the ears SLB
I see a duck but I always see one at a
time I don't see you know a complex to
the
Fields uh for which I have uh duck value
and rabbit value as
a computational System Mod I see a
rabbit or I see a duck and this is again
because my perception is embedded in
Prior Concepts I have about the world
and I know about rabbits I know about
duck and I will perceive either rabbit
or a duck knowing those are pretty much
two different kind of things I cannot
perceive
both so active in France entails that
perception works as I said it would
under practive processing but also that
actions work the same so in a sense
under active inference agents will
engage with the World by maximizing the
ban coherence which is predicting in a
sense the kind of predicting you do by
minimizing veral free
energy uh of central motor States with
PR belief through both perception and
action and what this means is that I for
example if I don't know about my uh what
is the water bottle I may glance at it
but also if I want water I will you know
take it I will expect myself to solve
the problem I have the fact I want water
and this is this expectation that will
lead to the sending of motor signals uh
that enable me to grab the bottle
this is a bit abstract because you know
cognitive
Neuroscience it's mostly math but I want
to make very clear why this
matters uh in
engineering signal engineering uh
control engineering this kind of stuff
there is a very wellknown problem that
is called the inverse problem if you
have a forward model of the world so how
things move and even if this model is
well known and well
behaved directly inferring what is going
on in the world requires to work not
with the forward model but with it
inverse and most of the time it's not
feasible let's take an
example what do you
see I will strongly expect that you see
a big blurred thing with red and orange
this is a painting of Willam Blake the
Ancient of Days and just by applying
bluring to it which is a very simple
process we all understand you can
destroy the information about it so that
you cannot tell what is going on with
the
painting and this is in general a
problem with any kind of inversion even
if you know the process that builds your
sensation you do not necessarily know um
how to infer what is going on from your
sensation and the same goes for motor
control even if you perfectly how your
body moves you don't necessarily know
what command to send to create this or
this or this
consequence and if you can calculate it
it will be very
costly and it will be likely very
fragile against both uh noise uh
ambiguity any kind of error in
perception
it will not it will be very very very
bad for adaptive control they hiding on
the run all the
time and uh active INF frence because
agents do not compute uh explicit
representation of the world but
comput or you know process physically
what they expect to sense and what they
expect to do given
context they can perform ative control
without being subject to the inverse
problem because there is no inversion
there is just a for model of what I see
what I do and this is why inference is
most likely correct in my opinion and
this is why uh it's very important in
context that your actions flow from
expectation and not from explicit
planning but this has nonrival
consequences for how we experence the
world I don't I don't know what I said
but it does have very obvious
consequences for how we experience the
world so because you anticipate in a
joint manner both motor States and sory
states you will experience reality as a
landscape AFF for denes where a fores is
a technical psychology term for
opportunity for Action so let's take
again the water
bottle the point would be that I do not
only see it as you know array of pixel
that are blueish I mostly see it as
opportunity for drinking and as
something that affs grabbing so I can
grab it I can drink for it and this is
something that is very basic in my
perception of the
bottle let's take another example so
this is a
path and if you look at the uh
color uh it's pretty much only green
everywhere you kind of see a thing in
the middle but you know from a pure
um colorometric statistical perspective
it's not obvious but you see a path this
is likely the first thing you saw about
this picture and if I remove it and I
wait a while ask you to remember what it
is I predict that you will remember
there is a path and there is green and
there are trees and if I ask could
remember exactly which trees are where
you will not remember that or you may
have an idea of it and now I put it back
will see that your idea of it is likely
false at least how it work every time I
could check in real life whether or not
people remembered precisely layout of
the things the point is you remember you
perceive from this picture
mostly the fact you can walk in the
center of it you perceive mostly an
affordance and you also perceive basic
person Concepts green trees but you're
keeping in mind only information that is
CRI IAL for you to navigate it and every
time you need more information you will
not take it from
a abstract model of everything that
exist in the world will just
glance and this is from that that you
have the impression of knowing a lot
about your environment because when you
don't know about something you can just
glance it's not because you have a full
presentation of everything you have seen
up to this point this would again not be
something competition
possible and what I take from this
notion of experiencing the world as a
landscape of for denes is that it
entails the disolution of agency as we
know it I have to say agency as we know
it because if I just say agency ND will
be upset and I do not want one to be
upset because it pays me so it will say
agency as we know
it in the sense that you do not have a
perception of the
worlds that you take as a array of facts
for taking decision that you then apply
everything is embedded when you see
something you already see what you're
going to do with it you already see the
valance that it hases for you both in
term of action that you can do in terms
of emotional consequences etc
etc your uh perception action Cycles are
not entailed by some kind of central
executive agency also executive function
do play a role they flow with yourself
model what you expect yourself to do be
context
and this means that context pretty much
decides for you in a sense at least it
can and this is from there that we build
the acting FR notion of uh social
evolution social
organization uh the idea that was argued
by R and by visier is that uh humans
will integrate a shap shape expectation
about agents such as themselves if I see
people stopping at a stop sign I would
infer that you have to stop at a stop
sign and that this is something that
applies to me personally and this means
that we develop a shared landscape of
cultural affordances affordances again
mean possibilities for action and
cultural affordances just mean that
those are culturally
constructed and those affordances they
you know are not just something that
exist in some abstract space that we
think about when we want and that we can
decide when we apply them and when we
don't they directly shape what we see
about the world and what we expect to do
so under active inference what we
actually do this is what I call embeded
normativity and this entails again that
we particip participatively
construct uh landscape that regulates or
at least participate regulate
at the very least
contextualize every single action and
perception that we can possibly do
everything and this see is a pretty
strong result and it seems that it can
explain you know a lot about op
evolution of culture but does
it we will now take a look at the formal
grounding of active
inference the bit of mathematics that is
understood to to land it most if not all
of its
legitimacy which is called the FY
principle we are getting into the math
stuff I'm sorry for those of you I don't
like it I promise it's interesting so if
we assume uh stochastic dial
system dmal means it moves stochastic
means it has a random
components and assuming that the system
is partition between a b e an agent a
boundary
environment and that uh the states of
the agent and the environment are
independent from each other given those
of B so all information you have about
a uh sorry all information that you
could have in E about a it's inside B
which is expressed in the equation in
the middle of the screen I don't want to
explain too much about it if you can
read it you can read it if not we'll go
back to something less mathematical
pretty
soon then there is what we call a
information geometry so a geometry of
the information that is in the
system and given states of a the agent
it gives you a belief a
distribution over the states of
e and this beliefs they minimize
rational F
energy so the thing that we said that if
it was verified it would entail creative
processing at
inference it is verified in theal case
given the statistical independence of
two system so pretty much everything
does cognition in the active INF
sets terms and and condition do apply to
the
statement so uh first when we talk about
um The Mark of blanket essentially what
we mean is that there is a individuation
there is an identity of the agent in the
environment in the sense
that it's a bit technical mathematically
but intuitively in the sense that they
are separated by something that the
agent can act on and the agent can sense
for example motor and sensory States and
the at least from a information
theoretic perspective interaction is
unlim mediated by states of the boundary
and again in the context of AC INF
France and the friendship principle it
is taken as the Criterion for the
existence of a as a individual
system something that also is very
important to this interactive active
inference thing is that the entire ID of
predicting one's own action uh depend on
a condition that we call strange part
Arles where uh there is no direct
observation possible effective States so
if I do not have a direct way to observe
what I do causally speaking my internal
states are not directly affected by
active States then you have this process
of predicting one's election and then
you have What Hoe phos ofer of friend
calls self-
evidencing so self- evidencing means
that in
an legent gathers proof of its own
existence through
action uh I hope you remember this
notion of basian coherence between a
model and sensory motor States this is
it if you maximize the basian coherence
between your prior beliefs what you
think the world is and what you think
you are in the world and what you
actually experience you're Gathering
proofs for a model that corresponds
pretty much directly to your own
existence so this is quite critical it's
the foundation stone over which this
entire active inference principle
because of
lies and so I'm you know accentuating it
a
bit what's important uh mathematically
is the relation between this notion of
model of the world and self model and
the active action and
perception that an agent um
enacts so we have to look a bit more at
the
mathematics
um I need to explain more mathematical
things a go Theory sorry is a
mathematical Theory where uh the
Dynamics of a system are caused by its
geometry more specifically by symmetries
in this system
so first we have to define the term of
symmetries symmetries are a familiar
transformation that do not affect a
system so for example what you can see
on the screen is the ceiling of the isar
mosqu and what you can see is that you
can just switch it a bit I did not
calculate how much precisely but you can
you know rotate it a bit and this won't
change the picture this won't change any
observable property of the system this
is what we call Symmetry and in this
case it is a discrete rotational
symmetry you can have a lot of symmetry
the principle is you can apply a
transformation to the system that
modifies nothing about
it and most physical forces that are
known are go theories electricity is a
go Theory uh weak force is a strong is a
we go Theory strong force is a gge
theory all of which are compatible in
their description draw it is another go
Theory which is not really compatible
with others for reason I do not will not
get into but in a sense you have a thing
called the Einstein ilber tensor that
described the geometry of SpaceTime
given the density of matter in it and
this tensor is by construction inv
variant under coordinate change you can
move it around it doesn't change the
system this is what we mean by
relativity and it is this symmetry this
symmetry is sufficient to entail the
entirety of Relativity Theory and the
entire idea of the geometry of space
time that you know causes a change in
the acceleration of
particles so this is NE this is a very
powerful mathematical tool that changes
you know complex equation into oh this
is
invariance that's
it and there is an argument there is a
pretty strong argument that active
inference is a goge
theory and it is a goge theory that uh
is entailed by the symmetries in the
probability of presence of the system in
a you know specific subart of the
system I need to spend a bit of time
over this actually the math is only
going worse from there you are one so
what you see on your screen the picture
is is the decomposition between the
conservative and the despective
components of the atomous flow of a
system on the left what you can see that
is wobbling around is a conservative
flow so it's something that I don't need
to explain the specific mathematics but
essentially this is what happens when
you throw a rock and there is no
exchange of energy there is no IR
evolution of the system and the dispa
component of the flow it is on the
contrary what happens
the attraction toward the specific
subset of the system that will take
energy to do its
stuff and when you you can decompose
anyx this
way and when you look at this system
what it does is that the dissipative
component of the flow will attract the
system toward the synchronization
manifold which is in a sense the most
likely trajectory of a system so for
example you will uh wake up drink coffee
go to the restrooms uh Drive walk to
work should you should walk to work I
guess uh work go to lunch Etc ET Etc
this how you do things and if you skip
some steps like you forget to eat
especially three days in a row you will
be in a pretty bad State and you will
won't be able to do uh your usual stuff
anymore and there is a force that
attacks on the Dynamics of your brain
and that enforces states that are at
least roughly coherent with this routine
most likely trajectory this is the
dissipative component of flow and this
is the gorge Force entailed by the
symmetries in the
probability um of presence of the system
the agent Nan system in its you know set
space okay this was abstract I'm
sorry and essentially there is argument
made by myself and sangta and friston
that uh because the Dynamics of the
system are pretty much set at least
within theal System Theory this Force
reduces to the dispersion of attention
given PR beliefs so if I'm thirsty that
was not a setup if I'm thirsty I will
pay attention to water and as we said
prior attention perception is always lad
on with value it's lad on with what you
can do with something
attention to the activity of opening my
bottle and starting to
drink I swear to you this was not me
setting up this I was thirsty and just
took the water bottle I did not think
about it this was not me making a
point
so um I would
say this is very nice all of this is
very you math I like math
but maybe we are running into a problem
of
circularity
because under active inference we accept
that the dyamics of the agent flow from
uh the beliefs of the agent their priors
and more specifically the symmetries in
those prayer
beliefs but also in the context of the
FP we take those belief to constitute
the attrac distribution of the agent for
system the actual probability of the
system to go there and there
so the beliefs are entailed by uh the
Dynamics which are entailed by the
beliefs there is a circularity problem
in that your def your definition of a
system uh well defines not only the
system but everything it can possibly do
this means you cannot have this you know
uh ruon type uh phenomena where your
structure produces is new activity Which
shapes the structure in no way because
again everything is entailed by the
symmetries of the
system and you could say renormalization
you could say path integral you could
say a lot of words
but and the system the FP is Def in the
context of Ni System Theory this is what
they do the stem theory is a theory
where um
you have a space like Dimension X you
have a time like Dimension T and you
have a function Fe that defines uh in a
sense a flow in time so a flow in zero
time is zero and a flow in T1 time and
then a flow in T2 time is equal to a
flow in T1 plus T2 time this is uh just
C
condition that entail that ensure this
is actually a flow in time and this
Theory represents with maximal
generality the evolution of a system
that is well defined that has an actual
aming space which evolves in time along
with Welling flow so that have physical
Dynamics let us
say and in essence this framing is not
General enough
to describe open-ended change or so I
would
argue and here we go in the how do you
say main course of this talk the notion
of contextuality is relation to active
inference core point I'm making so in
quantum physics we have to talk about
quantum physics I'm sorry I I said it
was only getting worse in quantum
physics um there is a you know well
defined physical space but there are are
somewhat weird and they are known to be
somewhat weird so we don't consider the
states of system per se we consider wave
function which are basically probability
solution over what could the system be
and those way function most of quantum
physics is defined by the action of
operators which are Matrix like linear
operators acting on wave function and
because of this
you can frame everything in quantum
physics almost everything as linear
algebra and then in linear algebra you
have a magic decomposition that tells
you that everything in context every
Matrix is characterized by igon vector
and igon values so for any operator you
can uh find a basis of vectors that
cover the entire State and each vector
when is just multiply by something when
you apply the operator to it and this is
sufficient to define the
operator so you take the operator e you
take a basis of X Lambda for different
Lambda and for each of this x Lambda e
appli to X Lambda is equal to Lambda
time x Lambda what is written on the
screen good
enough and
when in quantum physics you perform a
measurement on a system
X the outcome of this measurement is an
value for example it could be a energy
level and the probability that you have
to find the second value is equal to the
probability
of basically uh the wave function
projected on this Subspace corresponding
to the value so the sub space that if
you apply the operator to it is
multiplied by the good value and then
the system is updated by well
this uh the projection of its wave
function onto the
Subspace there is a bit of normalization
to do but in essence it's as it's
written so if you did not follow lot of
that not a problem I just need to
explain how cont meas work to introduce
the next concept that will actually do
the
work so uh there is is such a thing as
commutativity which exists when you can
apply two things in any order that you
like so for example you could have
operator and you can apply uh the E1
then E2 or you could apply E2 then E1
and there is no difference in anything
we call that
commutation if E1 and to commute then uh
you can measure any system in any order
and you will get the same results but
General case unless E1 any2 share igen
basis so the X
Lambda uh different application of the
two in different order will give you
different results with different
probability so this property means that
Quantum properties as they are
observable fundamentally depend on the
basis of measurements so the basis of
value with which uh you look at the
system and it is not just that there is
noise in measurements as you would have
in a classical system it is that the way
look at them fundamentally defines the
way they are postmeasurement and this
property is called
contextuality
okay so uh
contextuality is pretty related to plan
Evolution horis will see and it is not
something that you can uh integrate
within DST uh at least not with the
philosophy that uh the FP has and why it
use DST so if the time Dimension is
commutative so T1 plus T2 is equal to T2
plus T1 then the doesn't AFF
contextuality you can apply uh T1 plus
T2 or T2 plus T1 these are the same
thing this give the same results you
could decide that the time Dimension is
non commutative but then you do not have
a natural uning of time the evolution of
the system in the time Dimension becomes
a creative process where the agent could
go any different way that he likes with
different results so this is incoherent
with the physical intuition that is
behind DST as it's used by the F which
is to show the emerence of mindl
property beliefs from very simple
physical property Lal system property if
you just assume that your system is
somehow creative by construction yeah
you will get mindline property but
you're not explaining
it so uh this entails a kind of conflict
between active inference and um the
mathematical basis that it claims to
have so AC inference tells you that it
grounds the description of cognitive
agency cognitive
engagement by Taking Back
Dynamic the kind of stuff that you have
when you take a bunch of neuron and just
check
them uh be gical synchronization M
blanket so statistical Independence
blanket as we defined and because of the
FP we can say that this entails the
implicit prediction of sensor active
States and this grounds cognitive agency
this is the core claim of active
inference but classical L does not allow
to does not all the description of a
creative process where states of the
world like letters take a new meaning
and tell new Dynamics are made up along
the way it does not give you complexity
so it doesn't give you the constructive
aspect of cognition because this is the
same
thing now if we want to address this
mathematically we have to go in a kind
of weirder more esoteric
Direction uh specifically
what we get when we look at the
thermodynamics
observation so
observation when it is constrained by an
agent internal flow has to bring about
physical States uh in the sense of well
survivals that have a causal power on
things the reason for this is not some
weird uh pen rows or car stuff it's just
theonomics if You observe an object if
you are an agent s and You observe
object o you are getting information by
Lor principle this entails hitting so
this entails the creation of entropy
this entropy has to go somewhere so it
has to destroy information this is what
entropy is if you look at something and
you make it exist in the sense of uh
some observable that has caal power you
have to destroy the possibility for
observing something else so meaningful
obs ation observation that you remember
because if you forget about it you do
not have the same condition entails the
loss of
information in the
environment the lack of definition of
what you are not looking at because uh
of either hitting forgetting or Quantum
de
coherence the reason why is developed in
techark 2012 paper I won't explain the
mathematics now but I suggest you look
at
it and something that we
can claim from it if we are feeling ad
serious which I am is uh following F and
uh this schol of quantum B
asianism that you can pretty much reduce
Quantum cosmology so the construction of
space physical SPAC as we understand
them relies critically on context you
just need contextuality understood as
the construction of relevant observables
from the choice of context by the agent
and build from that
spaces so in the 2013 paper that I
putting here there is a
demonstration of this in a specific
subcase again I will not explain the
mathematics I will just say that uh the
mathematics IC work to show that it is
possible is ongoing there is no definit
demonstration that this is the math we
need to use but we have reason to
believe this exists there exists such
math and uh when we look at the role of
apologies I forgot to mention this idea
that physical spaces and physical
observables are brought about in an unal
sense by agency by choice of context by
agent is called paratory
realism and it's core to the Bist view
of cosmology Bist like AC
inference so when we apply this notion
of pp realism to
humans
um what I want to say and again I will
have to be a bit short on the math is
that assuming this uh thinking through
other mind thing from earlier assuming
that humans think of themselves as
instance of a human type that has
properties that has expected
action uh then and assuming
contextuality of course then successive
cycle of observation or
integration and an action of social
constraints understood as single
expectation over what you supposed to do
entails uh or at least enables the
description of a continuous proc cess of
open ended reconstruction of cure
landscape and this we know is opened
because of the contextuality which
affords by construction change this is
pretty much what it means and from there
we can have a dual understanding of the
integration and in action of constraints
or
Landscapes that are built culturally and
their evolution through the Contex of
the experience so a signal phenomenality
builds both commity structure and its
Evolution this is
nice so uh let us try to sum up what was
said
here uh first there is such a thing as
par participatory
realism um which claims that physical
spaces and physical observables are
built brought about by the agency of
observers in our case cognitive
agent and this applies to the specific
case of Human Social evolution by
claiming that the the relation between
structure so the Dynamics of a given
landcape and function so the meaning it
takes for individuals is a core driver
of many Evolution we have this ribbon
shaped thing where structure builds new
stuff which sorry builds new function
you meaning that shape structure in a
constructive way and this process cannot
be with DST because DST tells you what
the structure is it is what defines a
gical system the flow it has so you
cannot have evolution of flow within DST
it's not a
thing so to address this I propose to
borrow the antique regime that is
defined for quantum physics at least by
Quantum bism which is pism and which
states that the existence of stuff uh
observables spaces
deres from contextuality from the role
of context in defining physical
reality and uh from my own work and the
work of frosto I will claim that it
translates quite directly in the
contextual nature of cognition the fact
that we understand the world through
Concepts and not through you know inting
perception of what's out
there this applies in particular to the
case of uh human evolution Human Social
Evolution because we can describe
assuming AC inference and assuming that
a contextual interpretation of
it the Human Social and cognitive
activity can be described as the
construction and the action of a sh
system of social
constraints uh which shape public
behavior and private thoughts through
the expectation that they build over
behavior and over
attention and this is an illustration of
that process and The Duality it entails
between the enaction of structure and
its
reconstruction and what's interesting
with this concept is if you have
constraints and if you have a system of
constraint that is closed where each
constraint is brought about by other
bonds you have what mon moio to an
activist researcher Define as a form of
life as biological
organization and therefore this entire
contextuality thing not only explains
the evolution in the context of social
social cultural
Evolution but it also places this
contextuality at the center of you know
the constructive aspect of life so it
may be used to build the new mathematics
of life that accounts for organization
and open-ended
Evolution um this entails that humans
can be understood as a model well Human
Social cultural life forms can be
understood as a model for a broader
understanding of life and in that BR
understanding about life to to build it
we need first to understand how humans
set the context for social activity so
like thiser in a sense I think that this
is because we think about what we do in
a sense that is reflexive we have what
we call the existential stance which is
the attitude of reflecting over what one
would do in this context reflecting
about uh the interaction in disembodied
abstract
terms and this entails at least this
participate in the construction of many
things so for example uh taking roles
within interaction taking the role of
the EXP of the picture a designer
developer tester of software this
enables also to have a reflexive
understanding of what we mean by
specific acts as communicative acts so
this entails language and symbolism
this enables uh material symbolism in
the sense of monumentality shaping
materal landscape so as to build certain
meaning into this landscape and this
enable ritual the embodied synchronous
activity that is meant to have a
specific function that is meant to
entail specific norms and build specific
emotions all of this is part of how
humans set the context social activity
and all of this is stuffff for which we
have a lot of information so we can try
at least to build mathematics to
understand
that and I wanted to conclude on that
saying by Regenstein so you are saying
that human agreement decides what is
true and what is false it is what Humans
Beings say that is true and false and
they agree in the language they use that
is not agreement in opinion but in form
of
life which is my opinion the extent that
we understand interpret Stein just a way
to say that what is Meaningful what is
constraining in human activity is not
the specific nature the literal meaning
of a statement it's the choice of
framings and it's the context that is
set by the language used by people which
is my opinion a kind of visionary way to
understand to preface all of this
stuff so I was of course not able to say
a lot about the mathematic are really
the mechanics that I suppose about all
this stuff I had to stick to the basics
and I think you would agree that Basics
were you know a bit abstract so I would
strongly suggest that you look at uh the
stuff I wrote about this I have two
papers uh one on the right is
contextuality cognitive engagement in
France which is a quite barebones
argument that contextuality is indeed
intrinsic to cognition and critical to
explain what need change and the other
on the left from the existential stance
to constraints is a thicker more
committed arguments that indeed there
are such a thing as soci from life that
are entailed by social constraints
social constraints built by ex
existential stance as understood under
active inference so the entire program
so thank you for listening I hope that
it did not get to abstruct like
moderates acceptable on to acception and
I guess I will take uh on the
questions thank you AAL
awesome all right I'll I'll start with
writing uh with one question I wrote
down and then look forward to anyone's
questions in live chat
so how
do modeling and active inference
techniques like structure learning
Dynamic mark blanket detection language
like notations for generative models
deal or not with this question of the
open-endedness of life and
evolution depends which technique and
how it's applied I'd have to look at the
U find Prints but
you just to unpack why I'm asking and
then maybe it'll be a little clearer is
like you brought in this question of the
open-endedness so what is the
theoretical challenge
posed have prior methods been inadequate
and what would be the case if there were
some type of model flexible applications
that could could track open-endedness or
is that
impossible I don't want to commit on
possibility because uh I guess so all of
this relies on the idea that the choice
of State space is not natural it's built
by a system through its activity so I
don't want to commit to abstract
possible possible depends on what is
interesting to you in the process so uh
for example if I take structure learning
if you have some uh if you have some
mechanism to uh postulate New Concepts
through which a system will engage with
the world this is the kind of thing that
drives my change my point is not that
it's impossible to do my point is that
it's not underwritten by the FY
principle because the F principle is
fral Theory where you have a fixed
amount of stuff and specific flow in the
stuff space so if you want to do concept
learning you will have to postulate new
things and it won't be as physically
principal as it is under the
FP so what you would need to ground
physically this kind of stuff is
something else or maybe a more specific
updated version of the FP I don't know
but not something that is framed
strictly speaking within ecosystem
Theory
awesome makes a lot of sense okay I'll
ask a question from the chat anyone else
can
write okay Susan wrote do social
activities depend on individual
allostatic
capabilities allostatic oh
yeah like um how you say so the core
argument I would say that is in the
social constraint stuff is that um let's
say there is a coherence of what the
constraints are between individuals so
for example the concept of money applies
to you it applies to me applies to
anyone who lives pretty much in a urban
context uh that does not mean that it
applies the same to anyone money won't
mean the same for me or you as it would
mean for Elon Musk
because uh for example this is a okay
this is I'm getting Technical and
finance but uh people who are really
really rich like that are valued in
billions they do not actually have money
on their bank accounts what they have is
how do you say
actions um shares in stuff which is
valued billions and they use it as
leverage to get loans after loans after
loans after loans after loans so they
get free money basically this is not
money that they they spend um
so this does not mean the same thing
when we say money depending um on
whether we're considering the
perspective of you know working class or
even normal person a billionaire a bank
a state all these agent can engage with
money in different
Manner and uh you
can make sh up essentially you can
decide that no I don't do a 10 bill you
can invent new relate to thing you can
uh for example you can build a come on
pool a bank basically with friends it's
allowed you can do it you can build new
meaning into things and this is
something I don't know if you see my
cursor but that is entailed by the
integration of social constraints
because when I act in the context of
constraints okay I'm constrainted these
are constraint what I'm allowed to do
with them any anything I can do with
them basically I'm allow to project the
meaning and to build
I like and this means that this uh
system of constraint will change with
time because people will find new way to
use it to the advantage and yes this is
related to allostatic load this is
related to pretty much anything
including a bily signal that is relevant
for me to Define my strategy the
difficulty again is to repr
mathematically how novelty occurs
because we can't just track every single
state of everything and if we did that
still does not tell you where money is
there is no money parameter in the big
bank this is not the thing so money has
been made up people have been made up
Vision has been made up and the
core difficulty that I'm trying to point
out is to build mathematics that allow
for this kind of construction of
meaningful observable
States and yes again agenc is important
in it so allostasis is
how do you think that active inference
picks up on that challenge of being able
to model
that so uh conceptually there is the
entire inactive semiotics thing so
active inference allows you to think of
cognitive engagement
as something that's embeded in Concepts
uh so in agency and the context that
agents project into the world and this
is very good uh this is I think the why
we should think about perception action
uh problem is that the math do not
follow the math do not math um
again we justify active inference based
on framework that is built within
DST contextuality and therefore change
is not something that is afforded by the
SD there is uh so I assume someone in
the chat is saying yes but what about
what Chris Fields is doing yeah Chris
Fields is doing a strange categories
stuff that has I would say the
capability to show change because it has
very few mathematical constraint it does
not have the kind of constraints you
find within set theoretical approaches I
would say uh the issue is that you do
not have uh this basic intuition of just
be synchronization building new stuff
because the mathematical framework is
very general and it's not just bare
synchronization anymore it's I I don't
even know what it is it's info how you
say infom morphism I don't know what
infom morphism is like I have a
definition in mind but I do not know
what to do with it so I would say there
is a lot of work uh that remains to be
done to build meaningful phys physical
intuition about this process because
basically we have the choice between
math that are too constrained to
describe each change and math that is
not constrained enough to explain it in
terms of specific constraints and
specific patterns of
activity yes yes certainly that comes up
like what is the most General schema for
modeling a cognitive agent or cultural
agent it just a blank spec the less the
schema says the more General it is and
the less is there and the more degrees
of freedom and modler
is the free energy principle which your
talk also did a great job of bringing
into and out of quickly um is
architecture
independent it's some relationships and
and Frameworks that that meet in active
inference with the bottom up embodied
extended etc etc lineage and ecological
psychology and all of the actual model
constructivism and
instrumentalism and it's
it's it's interesting how uh yeah you
what do you think about
this I'm not try the where you're going
at I'm
sorry okay Jesse wrote the problem with
math and physics and any scientific
discourse is the models just are more
approximate of the error correction
criteria the errors are more approximate
of the error correction
criteria
okay um where are you continuing on in
your research and work like after seeing
things this way or is it laid out in the
papers or where else are you going with
it so I should really have done a part
in the talk about this r i so
essentially um I had to stop focusing on
the math because I had to look at the
sociology and I I have to have
to I have to have a proof of work for
this entire area of conent and I'm
focusing on this application to concrete
process of what I call ground building
so the construction of the set of Prior
that is shared by a community uh mostly
the two case studies that I've been
focusing on are the unification Church
which is
um Korean far right Christian Light cult
that among other things uh kept the
conservative Japanese party in power for
70 years Ed the journal Regan was weding
and according to CIA I did not verify
could a country in South America so as
you can see
very varant points for Cults and uh they
are mostly known because of their
ability to generate huge M panics around
their cive practices for Recruitment and
fundraising and so
I uh wrote a paper about um an active
Insurance approach to this um to this
recruiting and you know conversion
strategies which was successful um
because something we have with active
inference and that is hard to address
from a pure EOG ethnographic perspective
is the integration between you know the
Linguistics what we say and uh the base
cognition how we experience something
this is something that cogn cognitive
science cognition is something that
cognitive science studies pretty well I
think um and the other major case study
I've been uh working on is the
construction of the landscape in the SI
de balena which is archeological sites
studed by Escape where you have a lot of
FAL mounts that are you know playing
around and
who may or may not have a structuring
role in the navigation of the
area and so I've been doing Theory and
modeling on what's going on
there that is very
interesting Dare I ask how the Mounds
play a role in the navigation of the
area uh so it is claimed that basically
if you go from mount to mount you are
pretty close from a optimal path to
travel through landscape which is very
rid so it's not trivial to know where
you're supposed to go I would say the
non-trivial question is at least in
the context of the
did people intend to use the Mounds as a
you know landmarks to help with
navigation and I would say our core
point is that intent at least in the
common sense is not that important
because from the moment those PHS are
built they do shap the landscape like it
does not matter when you say this that
what you profoundly mean in your inner
self because there is no such thing as a
inner self there is what you do the
context in which you do it and how it
shapes the context and I would say this
is pretty core to this approach of
ground building that I've uh tried to
construct and
illustrate interesting it makes me think
about sort of the first and third
person biosemiotic
perspectives like when it comes to ant
colony phermone modifications of the
environment or nest
building intention wouldn't come so much
into play yet it may dominate aspects of
our
experience so considering well is the
biosemiotic event of the pheromone
perception or the mountain navigation or
or the reading or writing of an
environmental mark in what ways does the
causal consequence or experience from
the first person perspective Accord with
the
outside behavioral observation from the
third person perspective which sort of
strips the experience of
intentionality yet does so with methods
like intentional inference and and
inference to latent States proposed by
modelers so clearly part of the modelers
constraint
however the reference of those modeling
constraints is the biological constraint
so so I guess this is uh something
that's pretty critical in in the
approach I'm
proposing what we think of
intentionality pretty much does not
exist because uh the Baseline model that
we have in accidental safety is you have
a body and you have a mind and the mind
shows the body this is not a thing um
well you have a perception and you use
this perception to decide and act and
this is not a thing your perception of
the environment is integrated to
perception of yourself which is a direct
cause for your behavior so intentions
are embedded in the environments and
this is true for ants and the biosmetics
of you know um what's it called well
Fons
and this is true for Cults so for
example
uh there is a antire debate around are
the munis so the cult unification Church
cult are they con artists I don't know I
don't care I don't know if they believe
in what they say I I think they do I
don't think that changes the morals of
the situation because they have buil the
system and the system is bad and we do
not have we can just cize the context
what it is what makes people do and
again thinking about whether uh people
intend to build something bad in the
Deep of their inner selves is not a
meaningful question because there is no
such thing as in yourself there is what
you think to yourself it's a thing but
there is no self that is not embedded in
some context of operation this is not if
yourself is what you expect yourself to
do how you expect yourself to behave
your self
model that it's always elled in
something at least self talk there is no
way to escape
that so again there is no um let's say
the notion of intention that we can
motivate based on cognitive science
fields of conition it's much more
minimal than the stuff that we expect
and that we uh usually it take to be
necessary for
responsibility so there is a problem and
as far as I'm concerned this problem can
be solved from like sociologically by
the anal of premises by the analys of
well social constraints of the common
ground of social
interaction and I would be pretty
confident in it because if we can't do
that we can't do anything
cool um do you want to add any more
comments or what else are you thinking
about or how would you want to see
people pick this up and
continue uh read my papers that's the
simpler stuff I'm trying to do an advert
for them I'm trying to show relance at
least but again it's mostly math no one
understand math by talking that's not a
thing I don't think so at least so I
would highly recommend that you take a
look look at the paper which go in much
more detail about for example the
mechanics of social cognition as I
understand
them and I strongly suggest that you
look into the social sciences project on
the active influence of sorry the active
influence institutes that I am founded I
guess I can say that and send me
anything that you uh that you would want
me to look at and I will look at it and
I want to build new stuff from that this
is the core message and I think it's
pretty
possible pretty easy pretty constructive
productive good
things awesome I want to ask so many
questions about the social science
project but that's a great way to end it
and I I would look forward to it being
reactivated this year
too yeah let's do this cool thank you
a thank you
bye for